The following is a conversation with Jan Lekun, his second time on the podcast.
He is the chief AI scientist at Metta, formerly Facebook,
professor at NYU, touring award winner, one of the seminal figures in the history
of machine learning and artificial intelligence, and someone who is brilliant and opinionated
in the best kind of way, and so is always fun to talk to.
This is Alex Friedman podcast to support it.
Please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now here's my conversation with Jan Lekun.
You co-wrote the article, self-supervised learning, the dark matter of intelligence.
Great title, by the way.
Will he shine, Ezra?
So let me ask, what is self-supervised learning and why is it the dark matter of intelligence?
I'll start by the dark matter part.
There is obviously a kind of learning that humans and animals are doing that we currently are not
reproducing properly with machines or with AI, right?
So the most popular approaches to machine learning today are
or Pydheims, I should say, are supervised learning and reinforcement learning.
And there is too many efficient supervised learning requires many samples for learning anything.
And reinforcement learning requires a ridiculously large number of trial and errors to
for a system to learn anything.
And that's why we don't have self-driving cars.
That's a big leap for one to the other.
Okay, so to solve difficult problems, you have to have a lot of
human annotations for supervised learning to work.
And to solve those difficult problems with reinforcement learning, you have to have
some way to maybe simulate that problem such that you can do that large scale kind of learning
that reinforcement learning requires.
Right, so how is it that most teenagers can learn to drive a car in about 20 hours of practice,
whereas even with millions of hours of simulated practice, self-driving car can't actually learn
to drive itself properly? And so obviously we're missing something, right? And it's quite obvious
for a lot of people that the immediate response you get from people is, well, humans use their
background knowledge to learn faster. And they're right. Now, how was that background knowledge
acquired? And that's the big question. So now you have to ask, how do babies in the first few
months of life learn how the world works, mostly by observation, because they can hardly act in the
world. And they learn an enormous amount of background knowledge about the world that may be
the basis of what we call common sense. This type of learning is not learning a task, it's not
being reinforced for anything, it's just observing the world and figuring out how it works.
Building world models, learning world models. How do we do this? And how do we reproduce this
in machines? So self-supervised learning is one instance or one attempt at trying to reproduce
this kind of learning. Okay, so you're looking at just observation. So not even the interacting part
of a child. It's just sitting there watching Mom and Dad walk around, pick up stuff, all of that.
That's what you mean by background knowledge. Perhaps not even watching Mom and Dad just watching
the world go by. Just having eyes open or having eyes closed or the very active opening and closing
eyes that the world appears and disappears, all that basic information. And you're saying in order to
learn to drive, like the reason humans are able to learn to drive quickly, some faster than others,
is because of the background knowledge, they were able to watch cars operate in the world in the
many years leading up to it, the physics of basic subjects, all that kind of stuff. That's right.
I mean the basic physics of objects, you don't even know, you don't even need to know how
car works, because that you can run fairly quickly. I mean the example I use very often is you're
driving next to a cliff. And you know in advance, because of your understanding of
intuitive physics, that if you turn the wheel to the right, the car will be out to the right,
we'll run off the cliff, fall off the cliff, and nothing good will come out of this.
But if you are a sort of tabularized reinforcement learning system that doesn't have a model of
the world, you have to repeat folding off this cliff thousands of times before you figure out
it's a bad idea. And then a few more thousand times before you figure out how to not do it.
And then a few more million times before you figure out how to not do it in every situation
you ever encounter. So self-supervised learning still has to have some source of truth
being told to it by somebody, by some. And so you have to figure out a way without human
assistance or without significant amount of human assistance to get that truth from the world.
So the